I'm here to talk to you
انا هنا لاتحدث اليكم
about the economic invisibility of nature.
عن الغموض الاقتصادي للطبيعه
The bad news
الاخبار السيئة
is that mother nature's back office isn't working yet,
ان المكتب الخلفي للطبيعة الام لا يعمل حتى الان,
so those invoices don't get issued.
لذلك لم يتم اصدار الفواتير .
But we need to do something about this problem.
لكن نحتاج ان نقوم بعمل ما بخصوص هذه المشكله.
I began my life as a markets professional
بدأت حياتي كمتخصص في الاسواق
and continued to take an interest,
واكملت في هذا المجال,
but most of my recent effort
لكن معظم مجهودي حاليا
has been looking at the value
هو النظر في القيمة
of what comes to human beings from nature,
العائدة على الجنس البشري من الطبيعة
and which doesn't get priced by the markets.
والتي لم يتم تسعيرها من قبل الاسواق.
A project called TEEB was started in 2007,
في 2007 بدأ مشروع يسمى تيب,
and it was launched by a group of environment ministers
وتم اطلاقه من قبل مجموعه من وزراء البيئة
of the G8+5.
في مجموعة الدول 8 زائد 5
And their basic inspiration
وكان ملهمهم الرئيسي
was a stern review of Lord Stern.
هو مراجعة لتقرير لورد ستيرن عن التغير المناخي
They asked themselves a question:
طرحو على انفسهم اسئلة:
If economics could make such a convincing case
اذا كان بامكان الاقتصاد ان يقدم قضية مقنعه كهذه
for early action on climate change,
من أجل تحرك مبكر لتغير المناخ,
well why can't the same be done for conservation?
حسنا لماذا لا يمكن عمل نفس الشيء للحفاظ على البيئة؟
Why can't an equivalent case be made
لماذا لايمكن تقديم قضية مساوية
for nature?
للحفاظ على الطبيعة؟
And the answer is: Yeah, it can.
والاجابة كانت :نعم ,يمكن عمل ذلك.
But it's not that straightforward.
لكن ليس بطريقة مباشرة.
Biodiversity, the living fabric of this planet, is not a gas.
التنوع البيولجي.النسيج الحي لهذا الكوكب, ليس هو الغاز.
It exists in many layers,
انه يتواجد في عدة طبقات,
ecosystems, species and genes across many scales --
النظم الايكولوجي, الجنس البشري والجينات خلا عدة مؤشرات--
international, national, local, community --
عالمي, وطني, محلي ,مجتمعي--
and doing for nature
ويقدم للطبيعة
what Lord Stern and his team did for nature is not that easy.
ما قدمه اللورد ستيرن وفريقه للطبيعه ليس بتلك السهولة.
And yet, we began.
وبالكاد بدأنا.
We began the project with an interim report,
بدأنا مشروعن بتقرير مبدئي
which quickly pulled together
تم تجميعه على عجل
a lot of information that had been collected on the subject
الكثير من المعلومات التي تم تجميعها المتعلقة بالموضوع.
by many, many researchers.
من قبل العديد , والعديد من الباحثين.
And amongst our compiled results
ومن بين نتائجنا المسنخلصه
was the startling revelation
كانت الكشف المذهل
that, in fact, we were losing natural capital --
المتمثل في حقيقة اننا نخسر رأس مالنا الطبيعي--
the benefits that flow from nature to us.
المنافع المنسابه من الطبيعه الينا.
We were losing it at an extraordinary rate --
نحن نخسره بمعدل استثنائي --
in fact, of the order of two to four trillion dollars-worth
في الحقيقه, بمعدل يتراوح بين اثنين الى اربع تريليون من الدولارات
of natural capital.
من رأس المال الطبيعي
This came out in 2008,
ظهر ذلك في 2008,
which was, of course, around the time that the banking crisis had shown
في نفس الوقت الذي ظهرت فيه الازمات البنكية
that we had lost financial capital
حيث كنا نخسر راس مالنا المالي
of the order of two and a half trillion dollars.
بمعدل اثنين ونصف تريليون دولار.
So this was comparable in size to that kind of loss.
وذلك كان يكافئ لحجم الخسارة الاخرى.
We then have gone on since
وواصلنا في ذلك منذئذ
to present for [the] international community,
ان نعرض للمجتمع الدولي,
for governments,
للحكومات,
for local governments and for business
للحكومات المحلية و قطاع الاعمال
and for people, for you and me,
وللناس ,ولكم ولي,
a whole slew of reports, which were presented at the U.N. last year,
مستنقع كبير من التقارير , والتي تم عرضها في الامم المتحده العام الماضي.
which address the economic invisibility of nature
والذي حددت ملامح الاقتصاد الخفي للطبيعة
and describe what can be done to solve it.
وشرحت مالذي بوسعنا عمله لحلها
What is this about?
مالذي نتكلم عنه؟
A picture that you're familiar with --
صورة تعودتم عليها --
the Amazon rainforests.
الغابات المطيرة في الامازون.
It's a massive store of carbon, it's an amazing store of biodiversity,
انها مستودع ضخم للكربون, انها مستودع ر ائع للتنوع البيولوجي,
but what people don't really know
لكن الشيء الذي لا يعرفه الناس
is this also is a rain factory.
انها ايضا مصنع للمطر
Because the northeastern trade winds,
بسبب الرياح التجارية الشمالية الشرقية
as they go over the Amazonas,
اثناء مرورها فوق الامازون
effectively gather the water vapor.
تلتقط بخار الماء بفعالية
Something like 20 billion tons per day of water vapor
بمعدل 20 بليون طن من البخار يوميا
is sucked up by the northeastern trade winds,
تمتص بواسطة الرياح التجارية.
and eventually precipitates in the form of rain
واخيرا تترسب في شكل امطار
across the La Plata Basin.
فوق حوض "لا بلاتا "
This rainfall cycle, this rainfall factory,
هذه دورة الامطار, مصنع الامطار,
effectively feeds an agricultural economy
تغذي بفعالية الاقتصاد الزراعي
of the order of 240 billion dollars-worth
بما يمثل قيمته 240 بليون دولار
in Latin America.
في امريكا الاتينية .
But the question arises: Okay, so how much
لكن السؤال الذي يظهر. حسنا , كم تدفع
do Uruguay, Paraguay, Argentina
الاورجواي,الباراجواي,الارجتين
and indeed the state of Mato Grosso in Brazil
وايضا ولاية ماتو جروس في البرازيل
pay for that vital input to that economy
مقابل ذلك المدخل الاقتصادي
to the state of Amazonas, which produces that rainfall?
لولاية الامازون ,التي انتجت تلك الامطار؟
And the answer is zilch,
والجواب هو لا شيء,
exactly zero.
صفر تماما
That's the economic invisibility of nature.
ذلك هو الاقتصاد الخفي للطبيعة؟
That can't keep going on,
ذلك لا يمكن ان يستمر,
because economic incentives and disincentives are very powerful.
لان المحفزات والمثبطات الاقتصادية قوية جدا
Economics has become the currency of policy.
اصبح الاقتصاد هو عملة السياسة
And unless we address
ومالم نحدد
this invisibility,
هذا الخفي,
we are going to get the results that we are seeing,
سوف نجني النتائج الماثلة,
which is a gradual degradation and loss
والتي هي تدهور وخسارة تدريجيين
of this valuable natural asset.
لهذه الاصول الطبيعية
It's not just about the Amazonas, or indeed about rainforests.
ذلك لا يتعلق بالامازون فقط او الغابات المطيرة
No matter what level you look at,
لا يهم ما هو المستوى الذي تنظر اليه,
whether it's at the ecosystem level or at the species level or at the genetic level,
سواء كان مستوى التظام الايكولوجي,او مستوى الجنس البشري,او مستوى الجينات,
we see the same problem again and again.
نرى نفس المشكلة مرارا ومرارا
So rainfall cycle and water regulation by rainforests
اذا دورة هطول الأمطار وتنظيم الماء بواسطة الغابات المطيرة
at an ecosystem level.
في مستوى النظام الايكولوجي
At the species level,
في مستوى الجنس البشري
it's been estimated that insect-based pollination,
لقد تم تقدير ان التلقيح المعتمد على الحشرات,
bees pollinating fruit and so on,
مثل لنحلات تلقح الفاكهة وهكذا,
is something like 190 billion dollars-worth.
يساوي تقريبا 190 بليون دولار.
That's something like eight percent
ذلك يمثل 8 في المئة
of the total agricultural output globally.
من الناتج الزراعي عالميا.
It completely passes below the radar screen.
ذلك بالكامل يمر تحت شاشة الرادار.
But when did a bee actually ever give you an invoice?
لكن في الوقع متى ارسلت النحلة فاتورة لكم؟
Or for that matter, if you look at the genetic level,
او انك ذلك يعني شيئا, اذا نظرتم على مستوى الجينات
60 percent of medicines were prospected,
60 في المائة من الادوية تم التنقيب عنها,
were found first as molecules in a rainforest or a reef.
وجدت اولا كجزيئات في الغابات المطيرة او في سلسلة صخور
Once again, most of that doesn't get paid.
مرة اخرى, معظم ذلك لم يتم دفعه.
And that brings me to another aspect of this,
وذلك يقودني الى مظهر اخر,
which is, to whom should this get paid?
الا و هو ,لمن يجب دفع ذلك؟
That genetic material
تلك المواد الجينية
probably belonged, if it could belong to anyone,
من الممكن ان تتبع لاي جهة
to a local community of poor people
للمجتمع المحلي من الناس الفقراء
who parted with the knowledge that helped the researchers to find the molecule,
الذين شاركو في المعرفة التي ساعدت الباحثين على ايجاد الجزيء
which then became the medicine.
والذي اصبح دواء فيما بعد
They were the ones that didn't get paid.
اولئك هم الذين لم يتم الدفع لهم.
And if you look at the species level,
واذا نظرت على مستوى الجنس البشري,
you saw about fish.
تجد السمك
Today, the depletion of ocean fisheries is so significant
اليوم.نضوب الثروة السمكية في المحيط واضح للعيان
that effectively it is effecting the ability of the poor,
والذي يؤثر بشدة على قابلية الفقراء,
the artisanal fisher folk
من ممتهني حرفة الصيد
and those who fish for their own livelihoods,
والئك الذين يصيدون من اجل العيش,
to feed their families.
لاطعام عوائلهم.
Something like a billion people depend on fish,
حوالي المليون انسان يعتمد على السمك,
the quantity of fish in the oceans.
كمية السمك في المحيطات.
A billion people depend on fish
بليون انسان يعتمدون على الاسماك
for their main source for animal protein.
كمصدر رئيسي للبروتين الحيواني.
And at this rate at which we are losing fish,
وبهذا المعدل الذي نخسر به الاسماك
it is a human problem of enormous dimensions,
انها مشكلة انسانية ذات ابعاد هائلة
a health problem
مشكلة صحية
of a kind we haven't seen before.
لم نشاهد مثيلها من قبل.
And finally, at the ecosystem level,
واخيرا على المستوى الايكولوجي
whether it's flood prevention or drought control provided by the forests,
سواء كانت مكافحة الفيضانات او تحكم الجفاف والمقدم من الغابات
or whether it is the ability of poor farmers
او سواء كانت قابلية المزارعين الفقراء
to go out and gather leaf litter
للخروج وجمع بقايا الاوراق
for their cattle and goats,
لماشيتهم واغنامهم,
or whether it's the ability of their wives
او سواء كانت قدرة زوجاتهم
to go and collect fuel wood from the forest,
على الخروج وجمع الحطب من الغابات
it is actually the poor
في الواقع هم الفقراء
who depend most on these ecosystem services.
الذين يعتمدون بشكل كبير على خدمات النظام الايكولوجي
We did estimates in our study
قمنا بالتقدير في دراستنا
that for countries like Brazil, India and Indonesia,
انه بالنسبة لدول مثل البرازيل , الهند, واندونيسيا,
even though ecosystem services --
تلك الخدمات من النظام الايكولوجي --
these benefits that flow from nature to humanity for free --
تلك المنافع التي تنساب من الطبيعة للبشرية بالمجان--
they're not very big in percentage terms of GDP --
انها لا تشكل نسبة كبيرة من منظور الناتج القومي --
two, four, eight, 10, 15 percent --
اثنان,اربعة, ثمانية, عشرة, خمسة عشر في المائة--
but in these countries, if we measure how much they're worth to the poor,
لكن في تلك الدول, اذا قدرنا كم تساوي للفقراء,
the answers are more like
الاجابات هي
45 percent, 75 percent, 90 percent.
45 في المائة,75 في المائة ,90 في المائة.
That's the difference.
ذلك هو الفرق
Because these are important benefits for the poor.
لانها منافع مهمة للفقراء
And you can't really have a proper model for development
ولا يمكن ان يكون لديك نموذج جيد للتطور
if at the same time you're destroying or allowing
اذا كنت في نفس الوقت تقوم بتدمير او تساهم
the degradation of the very asset, the most important asset,
في تدهور اصول , الاصول الاهم,
which is your development asset,
والتي تمثل اصول التطور
that is ecological infrastructure.
تلك هي البنية التحتية اليكولوجية
How bad can things get?
الى اي مدى يمكن ان تسوء الامور
Well here a picture of something called the mean species abundance.
حسنا هنا صورة لما يسمى وفرة الانواع
It's basically a measure
انها بشكل رئيسي مقياس
of how many tigers, toads, ticks or whatever on average
لمتوسط عدد النمور, الضفادع, القراد , وما الى ذلك
of biomass of various species are around.
من الكتلة الحيوية من مختلف الانواع حولنا
The green represents the percentage.
الاخضر يمثل النسبة المئوية
If you start green, it's like 80 to 100 percent.
اذا بدأت بالاخضر , يمثل حوالي 80 الى 100 في المائة
If it's yellow, it's 40 to 60 percent.
الاخضر يمثل, 40 الى 60 في المائة.
And these are percentages versus the original state, so to speak,
وتلك هي النسب في مقابل الوضع الاصلي,
the pre-industrial era, 1750.
ماقبل الثورة الصناعية 1750
Now I'm going to show you
الان سوف اريكم
how business as usual will affect this.
كيف سوف يؤثر قطاع الاعمال هذا
And just watch the change in colors
فقط راقبو التغير في الالوان
in India, China, Europe,
في الهند,الصين, اوروبا,
sub-Saharan Africa
الصحراء الافريقية
as we move on and consume global biomass
كلما مضينا قدما واستهلكنا الكتلة الحيوية عالميا
at a rate which is actually not going to be able to sustain us.
وبمعدل سوف لن يتحملنا
See that again.
انظر الى ذلك مرة اخرى
The only places that remain green -- and that's not good news --
المناطق التي بقيت خضراء-- وذلك ليس بالاخبر الجيدة--
is, in fact, places like the Gobi Desert,
هي في الواقع اماكن مثل صحراء جوبي,
like the tundra and like the Sahara.
مثل التندرا ومثل الصحراء
But that doesn't help because there were very few species
لكن ذلك لن يساعد لانه يوجد هناك القليل من اصناف الحياة
and volume of biomass there in the first place.
وحجم الكتلة الحيوية هناك في المقام الاول
This is the challenge.
هذا هو التحدي
The reason this is happening
السبب في حدوث ذلك
boils down, in my mind, to one basic problem,
يتلخص ,من وجهة نظري, في مشكلة رئيسية
which is our inability to perceive the difference
هي عجزنا عن تصور الفرق
between public benefits
بين الفائدة العامة
and private profits.
والمكاسب الشخصية
We tend to constantly ignore public wealth
نحن نميل وبشكل ثابت الى تجاهل المنفعة العامة
simply because it is in the common wealth,
لانها ببساطة مكاسب عامة ,
it's common goods.
انها متاع مشترك
And here's an example from Thailand
وهنا مثال من تايلند
where we found that, because the value of a mangrove is not that much --
حيث وجدنا انه , بسبب قيمة شجر المنغروف ليست بذلك القدر--
it's about $600 over the life of nine years that this has been measured --
حوالي 600$ على مستوى تسع سنوات من الحياة حيث تم قياس ذلك--
compared to its value as a shrimp farm,
مقارنة بقيمة الارض كمزرعة جمبري,
which is more like $9,600,
والتي تساوي حوالي 9600 $
there has been a gradual trend to deplete the mangroves
كان هناك توجه تدريجي لتدمير المنغروف
and convert them to shrimp farms.
وتحويله الى مزارع جمبري
But of course, if you look at exactly what those profits are,
لكن بالطبع, اذا نظرت مالذي يعنيه هذا الربح,
almost 8,000 of those dollars
حوالي 8000 دولار
are, in fact, subsidies.
تذهب في الواقع كأعانات
So you compare the two sides of the coin
لذلك بمقارنة وجهي العمله
and you find that it's more like 1,200 to 600.
سو تخلص الى 600 في مقابل 1200
That's not that hard.
ذلك ليس بتلك الصعوبة
But on the other hand, if you start measuring,
ولكن في المقابل اذا بدأت في قياس
how much would it actually cost
كم تكلف فعليا
to restore the land of the shrimp farm
لاستعادة ارض مزرعة الجمبري
back to productive use?
مرة اخرى للاستخدام الانتاجي؟
Once salt deposition and chemical deposition
حالما رواسب الملح ورواسب المواد الكيميائية
has had its effects,
فعلت مفعولها
that answer is more like $12,000 of cost.
الاجابة هي 12000 $ من التكاليف
And if you see the benefits of the mangrove
واذا نظرت الى فوائد المنجروف
in terms of the storm protection and cyclone protection that you get
من منظور الحماية من العواصف والحماية من العصار التي تحصل عليها
and in terms of the fisheries, the fish nurseries,
ومن منظور مصايد الاسماك ومحاضن الاسماك
that provide fish for the poor,
التي تنتج الاسماك للفقراء
that answer is more like $11,000.
الجابة هي 11000$
So now look at the different lens.
الان انظر من زاوية اخرى
If you look at the lens of public wealth
اذا نظرت من زاوية الثروة العامة
as against the lens of private profits,
في مقابل المكاسب الخاصة
you get a completely different answer,
سوف تحصل على اجابة مختلفة بالكامل
which is clearly conservation makes more sense,
والتي تحافظ على معناها بوضوح
and not destruction.
ولا تدمر
So is this just a story from South Thailand?
هل هذه مجرد قصة من جنوب تايلندا ؟
Sorry, this is a global story.
للاسف,هذه قصة عالمية
And here's what the same calculation looks like,
وهنا مالذي تبدو عليه الحسابات الحقيقيه,
which was done recently -- well I say recently, over the last 10 years --
والتي تم عملها مؤخرا-- حسنا قلت مؤخرا , خلال العشر السنوات الاخيرة--
by a group called TRUCOST.
بواسطة مجموعة تسمى تروكوست
And they calculated for the top 3,000 corporations,
وقد اجرو حسابات لاكبر 3000 شركة
what are the externalities?
ما هي العوامل الخارجية؟
In other words, what are the costs of doing business as usual?
وبكلمات اخرى, ماهي تكاليف اجرء نشاطات تجارية في العادة؟
This is not illegal stuff, this is basically business as usual,
هذه ليست نشاطات غير شرعية، انها اعمال تجارية معتادة,
which causes climate-changing emissions, which have an economic cost.
والتي تؤدي الى انبعاثات كربونية تؤدي لتغيرات مناخية ولها تكاليف اقتصادية
It causes pollutants being issued, which have an economic cost,
وتؤدي الى احداث تلوث, له تكاليف اقتصادية,
health cost and so on.
تكاليف صحيه وهكذا
Use of freshwater.
استخدام مياه عذبه
If you drill water to make coke near a village farm,
حفرت المياه لعمل الفحم جوار مزرعة قروية,
that's not illegal, but yes, it costs the community.
ذلك غير شرعي وايضا له تكاليف في المجتمع.
Can we stop this, and how?
هل بامكاننا وقف هذا, وكيف؟
I think the first point to make is that we need to recognize natural capital.
اعتقد ان النقطة الاولى التي يجب اتخاذها هي ادارك ووعي راس المال الطبيعي
Basically the stuff of life is natural capital,
بشكل اساسي مستلزمات الحياة هي راس المال الطبيعي
and we need to recognize and build that into our systems.
ويجب علينا ان ندرك ونضمن ذلك في الانظمة
When we measure GDP
عندما نقيس الناتج القومي
as a measure of economic performance at the national level,
وكمقياس للاداء الاقتصادي على المستوى الوطني,
we don't include our biggest asset at the country level.
لم نضمّن الاصول الاكبر على مستوى الدولة
When we measure corporate performances,
عندما نقيس اداء الشركات,
we don't include our impacts on nature
لا نضمّن اثارنا على الطبيعة
and what our business costs society.
وماالذي يكلفه العمل التجاري على المجتمع.
That has to stop.
والذي يجب ان يتوقف
In fact, this was what really inspired my interest in this phase.
في الحقيقة.هذا هو الذي الهمني للاهتمام بهذا المجال
I began a project way back called the Green Accounting Project.
بدات مشروع فيما مضى يسمى مشروع المحاسبة الخضراء.
That was in the early 2000s
كان ذلك في اوائل 2000
when India was going gung-ho about GDP growth
عندما كانت الهند تمضي متحمسة حول نومها الاقتصادي
as the means forward --
ومايعنيه ايضا--
looking at China with its stellar growths of eight, nine, 10 percent
النظر الى الصين نموها الممتاز بمعدلات ثمانية,تسعة , وعشرة في المائه
and wondering, why can we do the same?
ونتساءل لمذا لا يمكننا عمل نفس الشيئ؟
And a few friends of mine and I
انا وبعض اصدقائي
decided this doesn't make sense.
قررنا ان هذا لا معنى له
This is going to create more cost to society and more losses.
ذلك سوف يوجد المزيد من التكاليف على المجتمع والمزيد من الخسائر
So we decided to do a massive set of calculations
لذلك قررنا عمل مجموعه هائلة من الحسابات
and started producing green accounts for India and its states.
وبدأنا في انتاج حسابات خضراء للهند وولاياتها.
That's how my interests began
وهكذا بدا اهتمامي
and went to the TEEB project.
ووصلت الى مشروع تيب
Calculating this at the national level is one thing, and it has begun.
حساب هذا على المستوى الوطني هو احد الاشياء ,ومن ثم بدأت.
And the World Bank has acknowledged this
والبنك الدولي اقر بهذا
and they've started a project called WAVES --
وبدأوا مشروعا اسمه ويفز WAVES--
Wealth Accounting and Valuation of Ecosystem Services.
حسابات الثروة و تقييم خدمات النظام الايكولوجي.
But calculating this at the next level,
ولكن حساب هذا في المستوى التالي,
that means at the business sector level, is important.
وهذا يعني اهمية مستوى قطاع الاعمال.
And actually we've done this with the TEEB project.
وفي الواقع قمنا بذلك مع مشروع تيب.
We've done this for a very difficult case,
قمنا بذلك لقضية صعبة جدا
which was for deforestation in China.
كانت لعملية ازالة الغابات في الصين.
This is important, because in China in 1997,
هذا مهم لانه في الصين 1997,
the Yellow River actually went dry for nine months
النهر الاصفر جف لمدة 9 اشهر
causing severe loss of agriculture output
ما تسبب في خسارة كبيرة في الناتج الزراعي
and pain and loss to society.
و ألم وخسارة في المجتمع.
Just a year later the Yangtze flooded,
فقط في سنة لاحقة فاض نهر يانجتزي
causing something like 5,500 deaths.
وتسبب في مقتل 5500
So clearly there was a problem with deforestation.
كان ذلك وبوضوح مشكلة متعلقة بازالة الغابات.
It was associated largely with the construction industry.
كان ذلك مرتبط بصناعة الانشاءات
And the Chinese government responded sensibly
واستجابت الحكومة الصينية بعقلانية
and placed a ban on felling.
وعملت حظر على القطع
A retrospective on 40 years
وبأثر رجعي لمدة 40 سنة
shows that if we had accounted for these costs --
يظهر ذلك اذا قمنا بحساب تلك التكاليف --
the cost of loss of topsoil,
تكاليف خسارة التربة السطحية
the cost of loss of waterways,
تكاليف خسارة الممرات المائية
the lost productivity, the loss to local communities
خسارة الانتاجية, الخسارة للمجتمعات المحلية
as a result of all these factors,
كنتيجة لكل تلك العوامل,
desertification and so on --
التصحر وهكذا --
those costs are almost twice as much
تلك التكاليف هي ضعف
as the market price of timber.
القيمة السوقية للخشب.
So in fact, the price of timber in the Beijing marketplace
لذلك في الواقع, قيمة الخشب في سوق بكين
ought to have been three-times what it was
يجب ان تكون ثلاثة اضعاف قيمتها
had it reflected the true pain and the costs
لتعكس الالم والتكاليف الحقيقية
to the society within China.
للمجتمع في الصين
Of course, after the event one can be wise.
بالطبع بعد الحادثة يكون الانسان حكيما
The way to do this is to do it on a company basis,
الطريقه التي يجب ان تقوم به بهذا هو ان تقوم به على مسويات الشركة
to take leadership forward,
لتتولى القيادة
and to do it for as many important sectors which have a cost,
وان تقوم به على القطاعات المهمة التي لها تكاليف
and to disclose these answers.
وان تكشف تلك الاجابات
Someone once asked me, "Who is better or worse,
سالني احدهم" من الافضل ومن الاسوأ,
is it Unilever or is it P&amp;G
هل هي شركة يوني ليفر او شركة بروكتل اند جامبل
when it comes to their impact on rainforests in Indonesia?"
من منظور تأثيره على الغابات المطيرة في اندونسيا؟"
And I couldn't answer because neither of these companies,
ولم استطع الاجابة لانه ولا واحدة من تلك الشركات,
good though they are and professional though they are,
على الرغم من كفاءتها واحترافها ,
do not calculate or disclose their externalities.
لم تقوما بحساب او كشف عواملهم الخارجية
But if we look at companies like PUMA --
لكن اذا نظرت الى شركة مثل بوما--
Jochen Zeitz, their CEO and chairman,
جوشين زيتز مدراءها ورؤسائها
once challenged me at a function,
تحدوني ذات مرة في مهمة
saying that he's going to implement my project before I finish it.
قائلين انهم سوف يطبقون مشروعي قبل ان انهيه
Well I think we kind of did it at the same time, but he's done it.
اعتقد اننا كنا على وشك ان ننهيه في نفس الوقت ولكنه انهاه
He's basically worked the cost to PUMA.
لقد قام في الأساس بعمل تكاليف لبوما
PUMA has 2.7 billion dollars of turnover,
بوما لديها 2.7 بليون دولار دورة مبيعات
300 million dollars of profits,
و 300 مليون دولار من الارباح
200 million dollars after tax,
200 مليون دولار بعد الضرائب,
94 million dollars of externalities, cost to business.
94 مليون دولار عوامل خارجية ,تكاليف للعمل
Now that's not a happy situation for them,
الان تلك لم تكن وضعية سعيدة بالنسبة لهم
but they have the confidence and the courage
لكن كان لديهم الثقة والشجاعة
to come forward and say, "Here's what we are measuring.
للقدوم نحوي والقول هذه هي تقديراتنا
We are measuring it because we know
نحن نقدرها لاننا نعرف
that you cannot manage what you do not measure."
انك لا يمكنك ادارة مالا تقدره."
That's an example, I think, for us to look at
ذلك مثال لنا لنتامل فيه
and for us to draw comfort from.
ولكي نستمد منه الراحة
If more companies did this,
اذا قامت شركات اكثر بنفس العمل
and if more sectors engaged this as sectors,
واذا تصدت قطاعات اكثر لهذا كقطاعات
you could have analysts, business analysts,
يمكن ان تحصل على محللين ,محللين اعمال,
and you could have people like us and consumers and NGOs
ويمكنك الحصول على رجال مثلنا ومستهلكون
actually look and compare the social performance of companies.
في الواقع انظر وقارن اداء الشركات.
Today we can't yet do that, but I think the path is laid out.
اليوم لا يمكننا عمل ذلك لكن اعتقد ان الطريق ممهد
This can be done.
يمكن عمل ذلك
And I'm delighted that the Institute of Chartered Accountants in the U.K.
وانا مسرور لان معهد محاسبين شارترد في المملكة المتحدة
has already set up a coalition to do this,
قد نظمت تحالف لعمل ذلك
an international coalition.
تحالف دولي
The other favorite, if you like, solution for me
المفضلة الاخرى كانت كحل بالنسبة لي
is the creation of green carbon markets.
هو انشاء اسواق الكربون الاخضر
And by the way, these are my favorites --
وبالمناسبة هذه مفضلاتي--
externalities calculation and green carbon markets.
حسابات العوامل الخارجية واسواق الكربون الخضراء
TEEB has more than a dozen separate groups of solutions
تيب لديها اكثر من 12 مجموعة متفرقة من الحلول
including protected area evaluation
بما في ذلك تقييم المناطق المحمية
and payments for ecosystem services
ومدفوعات خدمات النظام الايكولجي
and eco-certification and you name it, but these are the favorites.
وشهادة-الايكو او سمه ما تشاء,لكن تلك هي المفضلات
What's green carbon?
ماهو الكربون الاخضر؟
Today what we have is basically a brown carbon marketplace.
ماهو لدينا حاليا اسواق كربون بني
It's about energy emissions.
ذلك حول انبعثات الطاقة
The European Union ETS is the main marketplace.
الاتحاد الاوروبي اي تي اس هو السوق الرئسية
It's not doing too well. We've over-issued.
لا يقوم بعمل جيد
A bit like inflation: you over-issue currency,
تماما مثل التضخم تقوم باصدار العملات
you get what you see, declining prices.
تحصل على ما تراه ,انخفاض الاسعار
But that's all about energy and industry.
لكن كل ذلك بخصوص الطاقة والصناعة
But what we're missing is also some other emissions
لكن مالذي نفتقده هنا هو نوع اخر من الانبعاثات
like black carbon, that is soot.
مثل الكربون الاسود , انه السخام
What we're also missing is blue carbon,
مالذي نفتقده هنا هو الكربون الازرق,
which, by the way, is the largest store of carbon --
والذي هو بالمناسبة اكبر مخزن للكربون
more than 55 percent.
اكثر من 55 بالمائة
Thankfully, the flux, in other words, the flow of emissions
الحمد لله,المد ,از بعبارة اخرى, تدفق الانبعاثات
from the ocean to the atmosphere and vice versa,
من المحيط الى الغلاف الجوي وبالعكس
is more or less balanced.
اقل في الميزان
In fact, what's being absorbed
في الواقع ما تم امتصاصه
is something like 25 percent of our emissions,
هو 25 في المائة من انبعاثاتنا
which then leads to acidification
والذي يؤدي الى حامضية
or lower alkalinity in oceans.
او نقص القلوية في المحيطات
More of that in a minute.
المثير من ذلك في دقيقة
And finally, there's deforestation,
واخيرا, هناك ازالة الغابات،
and there's emission of methane
وهناك انبعاثات الميثان
from agriculture.
من الزراعه
Green carbon,
الكربون الاخضر
which is the deforestation and agricultural emissions,
والذي هو انبعاثات ازالة الغابات و الزراعه
and blue carbon
والكربون الازرق
together comprise 25 percent of our emissions.
مجتمعه تشكل 25 في المائة من انبعاثاتنا
We have the means already in our hands,
والمعنى موجود في ايدينا
through a structure, through a mechanism, called REDD Plus --
من خلال البنية,و الالية, وتسمى ريد بلاس
a scheme for the reduced emissions
مخطط لتقليل الانبعاثات
from deforestation and forest degradation.
من ازالة الغابات و تقلص الغابات
And already Norway has contributed a billion dollars each
وقد قامت النرويج بالمساهمة ببليون دولار
towards Indonesia and Brazil
لاجل اندونسيا والبرازيل
to implement this Red Plus scheme.
لتطبيق مخطط ريد بلاس
So we actually have some movement forward.
اذاً لدينا بعد التحركات للامام
But the thing is to do a lot more of that.
لكن المهم ان نقوم بالكثير من ذلك
Will this solve the problem? Will economics solve everything?
هل سيقوم ذلك بحل المشكلة؟ هل يقوم الاقتصاديون بحل كل شيء
Well I'm afraid not.
اخشى انه لا
There is an area that is the oceans, coral reefs.
هناك منطقة في المحيط ,الشعاب المرجانية.
As you can see,
كما تشاهدون
they cut across the entire globe
تقطع خلال العالم باكمله
all the way from Micronesia
كم ميكرونيزيا
across Indonesia, Malaysia, India, Madagascar
خلال اندونسيا , ماليزيا, الهند, مدغشقر
and to the West of the Caribbean.
الى الغرب من الكاريبيان
These red dots, these red areas,
تلك النقاط الحمرا تلك المناطق الحمراء
basically provide the food and livelihood
بشكل اساسي تقدم الطعام والرزق
for more than half a billion people.
لاكثر من نصف بليون انسان
So that's almost an eighth of society.
وذلك تقريبا ثمن المجتمع
And the sad thing is that, as these coral reefs are lost --
والشيء المحزن ان تلك الشعاب المرجانية قد اختفت
and scientists tell us
ويخبرنا العلماء
that any level of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere above 350 parts per million
ان اي مستوى من ديوكسيد الكروبن في الغلاف الجوي فوق مستوى 350 جزء لكل مليون
is too dangerous for the survival of these reefs --
هو خطير جداً لحياة تلك الشعاب
we are not only risking the extinction
نحن لا نواجه الانقراض فقط
of the entire coral species, the warm water corals,
لصنف الشعاب, شعاب المياه الدافئة,
we're not only risking a fourth of all fish species which are in the oceans,
نحن لا نواجه ربع صنف الاسماك في المحيطات
but we are risking the very lives and livelihoods
لكننا نجازف بانواع الحياة وسبل العيش
of more than 500 million people
لأكثرمن 500 مليون انسان
who live in the developing world in poor countries.
والذين يعيشون في العالم النامي في بلدان فقيرة
So in selecting targets of 450 parts per million
لذلك فان اختيار هدف 450 جزء لكل مليون
and selecting two degrees at the climate negotiations,
واختيار درجتين لمفاوضات المناخ
what we have done is we've made an ethical choice.
ما فعلناه اننا عملنا خيار اخلاقي
We've actually kind of made an ethical choice in society
نحن في الواقع أخترنا اخلاقيا
to not have coral reefs.
أن لا يكون لدينا شعاب مرجانية
Well what I will say to you in parting
الذي سوف اقوله لكم
is that we may have done that.
انه ربنما عملنا ذلك
Let's think about it and what it means,
دعونا نفكر فيه وفي معناه
but please, let's not do more of that.
لكن ارجوكم لا تقومو بالكثير من ذلك
Because mother nature only has that much
لان الطبيعة الام لديها فقط ذلك القدر
in ecological infrastructure and that much natural capital.
في البنية التحتية الايكولوجية وذلك القدر من راس المال الطبيعي
I don't think we can afford too much of such ethical choices.
لا اعتقد اننا سنتحمل الكثير من تلك لخيارات الاخلاقية
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)